The Victor D'Amico Papers
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
- Series IV. Children's Art Carnival and Caravan, 1940s-1979 (bulk 1942-1965)
  - Subseries IV.A. Children's Art Carnival, 1940s-1979 (bulk 1942-1965)
    Among D'Amico's most widely known and experienced innovations was the creation of both the space and opportunity for children to create art, in a location and with equipment and supplies specifically designed by him and dedicated only to that end. Referred to here as the Children's Art Carnival, it was termed, at various times, the Children's Holiday Circus, Children's Holiday Carnival, Children's Festival of Modern Art, and Children's Art Carnival. The first Children's Holiday Carnival at MoMA opened in 1942, and was held annually at the Museum until 1952, and after 1955, often in conjunction with similarly themed exhibitions (see Series VI. MoMA Exhibitions).
    Designed in two parts, the Children's Art Carnival consisted of an area with so-called motivations, followed by one in which art materials and teachers were available. According to D'Amico's Experiments in Creative Art Teaching, this would show "how children respond to art experiences under ideal teaching in a stimulating environment…" The Carnival accommodated children who could fit through a cut-out silhouette of their maximum sizes that formed the Carnival's entrance. The television program "Through the Enchanted Gate" (see Subseries IV.B) was conceived as the Children's Art Carnival for home consumption by families.
    In 1957, the Children's Art Carnival traveled to Barcelona and Milan as a feature of the International Samples Fair. For six months in 1958, it was part of the American pavilion at the Brussels World's Fair. There, close to 17,000 children from around the world participated, as well as 2,000 teachers. In March 1962, at the invitation of Indira Gandhi, First Lady Jacqueline Kennedy presented a version of the Carnival in New Delhi to the children of India, on behalf of the International Council of The Museum of Modern Art and the Asia Society. D'Amico attended its opening in October 1963. It traveled to the major cities of India, where it was visited by an estimated 38,000 children, before being returned to New Delhi as a training center for Indian teachers.
    After D'Amico's retirement, the Children's Art Carnival opened in permanent form in Harlem in 1969, under the direction of Betty Blayton Taylor. Its first three years were funded through a committee chaired by Mrs. John D. (Blanchette) Rockefeller III.
    The subseries is organized chronologically by locations of the Children's Art Carnival into seven subseries. Some original folders included photographs from multiple locations: these are included as the last subseries.
    Subseries IV.A.i. MoMA and General,1942-1979
    Subseries IV.A.ii. Milan,1956-1957
    Subseries IV.A.iii. Barcelona,1957
    Subseries IV.A.iv. Brussels,1958-1959
    Subseries IV.A.v. Harlem,1960-1975
    Subseries IV.A.vi. India,1960s-1964, 1969
    Subseries IV.A.vii. Multiple Locations,1940s-1960s
  - Subseries IV.A.i. MoMA and General, 1942-1979
    - Children attending the Carnival, installation views, 1942-1944; Includes images from Art in Progress: 15th Anniversary Exhibition[MoMA Exh. #258]: b/w prints (Box 16, Folder IV.A.i.1)
    - Clippings, MoMA press release, 1943-1944, 1951, 1958; Includes list of works in Children's Holiday Carnival of Modern Art[MoMA Exh. #496, December 4, 1951-January 6, 1952] (Box 16, Folder IV.A.i.2)
    - Children attending the Carnival, installation views, 1944-1945; B/w prints (Box 16, Folder IV.A.i.3)
    - Children attending the Carnival, installation views, 1946-1947; B/w prints (Box 16, Folder IV.A.i.4)
    - Floor and lighting plans, 1946, 1949; Original drawings, whiteprints; oversize, see flat file 2-2 (Box flat file 2-2, Folder IV.A.i.5*)
    - Press releases, draft text for release, 1948, 1955, 1956, 1960 (Box 17, Folder IV.A.i.6)
    - Children attending the Carnival, installation views, list of captions for images, 1949-1950; B/w prints (Box 17, Folder IV.A.i.7)
    - Children attending the Carnival, installation views, 1949-1950; B/w prints mounted on pages previously removed from album; some pages have typed captions (Box 17, Folder IV.A.i.8)
    - Children attending the Carnival, installation views, 1950s; B/w prints (Box 17, Folder IV.A.i.9)
    - Documentation of one young girl's experience of the Carnival, [1950s]; Photographs by Aaron Haberfeld: b/w prints (Box 17, Folder IV.A.i.10)
    - Press coverage, 1950-1965; Includes articles from Interiors,Florida Art Education Art News,The New York Times, unidentified publications (Box 17, Folder IV.A.i.11)
    - Children attending the Carnival, installation views, 1952-1953; B/w prints (Box 17, Folder IV.A.i.12)
    - Children attending the Carnival, installation views, 1953-1954; B/w prints (Box 17, Folder IV.A.i.13)
    - Children attending the Carnival, installation views, 1955-1956; B/w prints (Box 17, Folder IV.A.i.14)
    - Plan of first floor gallery, 1955-1956; Drawing, tracings, whiteprints (some hand annotated) (Box 72, Folder IV.A.i.15*)
    - Children attending the Carnival, installation views, 1955-1958; B/w prints (Box 17, Folder IV.A.i.16)
    - CBS TV program "Let's Take a Trip", December 23, 1956; Whiteprint floor plan with hand annotations (Box 72, Folder IV.A.i.17*)
    - CBS TV program "Let's Take a Trip", December 1956; Expenses, location information, CBS press release, script for program aired on December 23, 1956 (Box 17, Folder IV.A.i.18)
    - “Understanding Children’s Creativeness”, 1956-1957; Continuous slide show for parents, demonstrating how to understand and respect children's art efforts and suggesting art materials and ideas for home use; arranged by instructor Jane Cooper Bland: positive and negative b/w transparencies (Box 18, Folder IV.A.i.19)
    - Children attending the Carnival, installation views, 1956-1958; B/w prints, color transparencies (Box 18, Folder IV.A.i.20)
    - Designs for educational equipment and furniture, 1956-1957; Tracings, whiteprints, photostats (Box 72, Folder IV.A.i.21*)
    - Proposed plans (rejected), 1957; Tracings, whiteprints, photostats (Box 72, Folder IV.A.i.22*)
    - Children attending the Carnival, installation views, 1959; B/w prints (Box 18, Folder IV.A.i.23)
    - Children's Summer Art Carnival: construction, installation, plumbing, and painting plans, 1959-1960; Tracings, whiteprints, photostats (Box 72, Folder IV.A.i.24*)
    - Children making art, [1960s]; Color slides, 4x5 color transparencies (Box 18, Folder IV.A.i.25)
    - Carnival, [1960s]; 7" audio reel; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 18, Folder IV.A.i.26)
    - Art - A Human Necessity: "On back Carnival", [1960s]; 7" audio reel; NOTE: This sound recording was preserved in Spring, 2013. In addition to the original, a Broadcast Wave File (BWF) archival master, a DVD audio master, and a CD-R use copy now exist. (Box 18, Folder IV.A.i.27)
    - "Save Children's Art Carnival V[ictor] E[.] D['Amico]", [1960s-1970s]; Standard audio cassette (Box 18, Folder IV.A.i.28)
    - Children's Holiday Carnival of Modern Art, [1960s]; 7" film reel; NOTE: This 7" film reel has been transferred to the Museum's Film Study Center, which has the proper facilities for storing and screening them. Researchers should contact the Study Center for further information. Access may be denied due to the film's physical condition. (Box 18, Folder IV.A.i.29)
    - Published information, 1960, 1964, 1979; Includes 1960 MoMA publication "Today and Tomorrow"; "Children’s Art Carnival Report: The Children's Art Carnival in India, 1963-1964"; and clipping from School Arts(October 1979) (Box 18, Folder IV.A.i.30)
    - Children at Children's Art Carnival; view of MoMA garden; Mondrian work; model of Children's Art Caravan, 1963, undated; Color slides organized from unsorted materials (Box 18, Folder IV.A.i.31)
    - Gallery photographs, motivational toys, art work, 1968; Color, b/w slides (Box 14, Folder IV.A.i.32)
  - Subseries IV.A.ii. Milan, 1956-1957
    - Floor plan of U.S. exhibit and Children’s Art Carnival, January 1, 1956; Original tracings and whiteprints; oversize, see flat file 2-2 (Box flat file 2-2, Folder IV.A.ii.1*)
    - Children and families participating, April 1957; B/w prints (Box 18, Folder IV.A.ii.2)
    - Staff, galleries, April 1957; B/w print, 8x10 negatives (Box 18, Folder IV.A.ii.3)
    - Children at work, finished works, [April 1957]; Color and b/w slides, some glass-mounted (Box 19, Folder IV.A.ii.4)
    - Correspondence, April-June 1957; Includes letters to D'Amico from children who attended the fair (Box 19, Folder IV.A.ii.5)
    - Trip to Italy, 1957; Includes correspondence, sightseeing and hotel suggestions, shipping information for Carnival items (Box 19, Folder IV.A.ii.6)
    - Promotional and publicity materials, 1957; Includes clippings, brochure (in Italian), MoMA press release (Box 19, Folder IV.A.ii.7)
    - Children participating, 1957; Color, b/w slides (Box 19, Folder IV.A.ii.8)
  - Subseries IV.A.iii. Barcelona, 1957
    - Floor plan, March 10, 1957; Whiteprint; oversize, see flat file 2-2 (Box flat file 2-2, Folder IV.A.iii.1*)
    - Lighting plan, interior and exterior elevations, installation diagrams for equipment and toys, floor plans, 1957; Tracings, whiteprints, photostats (Box 73, Folder IV.A.iii.2*)
    - Children participating, school groups, 1957; B/w prints (Box 19, Folder IV.A.iii.3)
    - Children participating, school groups, 1957; B/w prints (Box 19, Folder IV.A.iii.4)
    - Confidential report on MoMA in Barcelona to D'Amico by Moreen Maser, [1957]; Summary, observations, recommendations, diary of events: original typescript (Box 19, Folder IV.A.iii.5)
  - Subseries IV.A.iv. Brussels, 1958-1959
    - Floor plans, designs for educational materials, [early] 1958; Original drawings, tracings, and whiteprints; termed "Children's Creative Art Center" on drawings (Box 73, Folder IV.A.iv.1*)
    - Publicity, April 1958; MoMA press release, clipping (Box 19, Folder IV.A.iv.2)
    - Press coverage, April-June 1958; Clippings from American newspapers (Box 19, Folder IV.A.iv.3)
    - Press coverage, May-October 1958; Articles in French-language consumer magazines (Box 19, Folder IV.A.iv.4)
    - Press coverage, May-October 1958; Special issue of Paris Match on exposition; removed from folder IV.A.iv.4 (Box 70, Folder IV.A.iv.5*)
    - Press coverage, July-August 1958; Clippings from French-language newspapers (Box 19, Folder IV.A.iv.6)
    - Correspondence, May 1958-January 1959; D'Amico letters to and from teachers Lois Lord, Susan Lynn, and J. Eugene Grigsby, Jr. (Box 19, Folder IV.A.iv.7)
    - Correspondence, July-October 1958; Letters to D'Amico from teachers Jane Cooper Bland, Charles Alston, and Margaret Stark during the fair. Some letters accompany reports on activities and attendance. (Box 19, Folder IV.A.iv.8)
    - Correspondence, September-October 1958; Includes letters from Carnival attendees, in French (some with English translations) (Box 19, Folder IV.A.iv.9)
    - Children participating, installation photographs, finished works, 1958; Color, b/w slides (Box 19, Folder IV.A.iv.10)
    - Children participating, finished works, 1958; Color slides (Box 19, Folder IV.A.iv.11)
    - Children participating, children and teachers, 1958; B/w prints, 8x10 negatives, 35 mm negatives (Box 19, Folder IV.A.iv.12)
    - Children participating, 1958; Pages removed from album inscribed to D'Amico by Susie Lynn: b/w prints (Box 20, Folder IV.A.iv.13)
    - Press coverage, 1958; Includes official guidebook to the Brussels World's Fair, summaries of press coverage, press releases (Box 20, Folder IV.A.iv.14)
    - Publicity, 1958; Carbon typescript of article by Jane Bland and Lois Lord; article by Eugene Grigsby in Pacific Arts Association Bulletin (Box 20, Folder IV.A.iv.15)
    - "Miscellaneous souvenirs", 1958; Includes original artwork by Belgian children who attended the fair (Box 20, Folder IV.A.iv.16)
    - Paper shopping bags, 1958; Promotional items created for the fair (Box 70, Folder IV.A.iv.17*)
    - CBS News coverage, [1958]; 11" film reel; NOTE: This 11" film reel been transferred to the Museum's Film Study Center, which has the proper facilities for storing and screening it. Researchers should contact the Study Center for further information. Access may be denied due to the film's physical condition. (Box 20, Folder IV.A.iv.18)
  - Subseries IV.A.v. Harlem, 1960-1978
    - Children attending the Carnival, exterior views, 1960-1969; B/w prints, negatives (Box 20, Folder IV.A.v.1)
    - Establishment, 1968-1969; Includes proposals, agreement between MoMA and Harlem School of the Arts, correspondence (Box 20, Folder IV.A.v.2)
    - Fundraising, 1968-1972; Includes correspondence, reports, requests for funding (Box 20, Folder IV.A.v.3)
    - Press releases, brochures, correspondence, class schedules, 1968-1973, 1978 (Box 20, Folder IV.A.v.4)
    - Press releases, clippings, schedules, 1969-1975; Includes photocopied grant application to the New York State Council on the Arts (Box 20, Folder IV.A.v.5)
    - Press releases, clippings, schedules, proposed budgets, 1969-1975; Includes list of Carnival contributors, 1969-1973 (Box 20, Folder IV.A.v.6)
    - Interior views, [1970s]; Color slides (Box 20, Folder IV.A.v.7)
    - Interior views, [1970s]; Color slides (Box 20, Folder IV.A.v.8)
    - Interior and exterior views, 1970-1974; Color slides (Box 20, Folder IV.A.v.9)
    - Sample calendar, 1971; Proposed promotional item, using images of children’s art work (Box 20, Folder IV.A.v.10)
    - “Carnival of the Mind”, 1971; Includes planning material and proposal for television project: “a series of projects concerned with mass media education in creative thinking” (Box 20, Folder IV.A.v.11)
    - Press release, 10th anniversary announcement, 1978 (Box 20, Folder IV.A.v.12)
  - Subseries IV.A.vi. India, 1960s-1964, 1969
    - Historical background information, [1960s]; Extracts from the will and testament of Jawaharlal Nehru (6/21/1954) specifying disposal of his body after death: carbon typescript; 1896 correspondence from Caspar Purdon Clarke, Director of the South Kensington Museum, to Sir George C.M. Birdwood: photocopy. There is no explanation for the presence of these documents in the collection. (Box 20, Folder IV.A.vi.1)
    - Presentation portfolio, photo captions, MoMA press release, photo of Jacqueline Kennedy and Indira Gandhi, March 1962; A similar portfolio was presented by Mrs. Kennedy to Mrs. Gandhi when the former donated the Children's Art Carnival to India in 1962 (Box 70, Folder IV.A.vi.2*)
    - Designs for educational equipment and furniture, installation and lighting plans, June 1962; Tracings, whiteprints, photostats (Box 73, Folder IV.A.vi.3*)
    - Designs for educational equipment, toys, June 1962; Whiteprints (Box 73, Folder IV.A.vi.4*)
    - Original and photocopied press coverage, program, June 1962-December 1963 (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.5)
    - "India trip not including Carnival", 1962; Tray I: color slides removed from a carousel (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.6)
    - "India trip not including Carnival", 1962; Tray II: color slides removed from a carousel (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.7)
    - "India trip not including Carnival", 1962; Tray IV: color slides removed from a carousel [no Tray III] (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.8)
    - "India trip not including Carnival", 1962; Tray V: color slides removed from a carousel (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.9)
    - "India trip not including Carnival", 1962; Tray VI: color slides removed from a carousel (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.10)
    - Poster, 1962; Photo reproductions (Box 73, Folder IV.A.vi.11*)
    - Unidentified wall text describing India Carnival, [1962]; B/w slides (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.12)
    - Children at Art Carnival, Mrs. Indira Gandhi and other officials, 1962-1963; Includes 12 frames of 16 mm moving image film of Jacqueline Kennedy and Mrs. Gandhi: b/w prints (one mounted) and negatives, 16 mm film, color transparencies (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.13)
    - Photocopied news clippings, original correspondence, schedule for D'Amico and party in India, report on Carnival in India, 1962-1964, 1969; Includes 1969 clipping re: Arlette Buchman presentation on Art Carnival (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.14)
    - Press clippings (1 of 2), September, October 1963; Loose clippings and pages from an album; in English and Hindi (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.15)
    - Press clippings (2 of 2), September, October 1963; Loose clippings and pages from an album; in English and Hindi (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.16)
    - Children, teachers, finished works, 1963; Color slides (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.17)
    - Teachers and students, building interior and exterior, travel photos of Delhi and environs, 1963; Color slides removed from a carousel (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.18)
    - Students working: with D'Amico, with Indira Gandhi, 1963; B/w prints (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.19)
    - Students, teachers, finished works, 1963; Color slides organized from unsorted materials (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.20)
    - Department of Education plans, 1963; Pencil sketch, list of drawings for the Carnival in India (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.21)
    - Staff and children, 1963; Identified as being from Dutia Photo Service, New Delhi: b/w prints and negatives (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.22)
    - India, 1963; B/w negatives, prints (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.23)
    - Madras, Ahmadabad, Hyderabad, Bangalore, 1963; Captioned b/w negative strips (Box 21, Folder IV.A.vi.24)
  - Subseries IV.A.vii. Multiple Locations, 1940s-1960s
    - Children participating, installation views (1 of 6), [1940s-1960s]; From a set of mounted, numbered variously, b/w prints that also include MoMA exhibitions and classes (Box 22, Folder IV.A.vii.1)
    - Children participating, installation views (2 of 6), [1940s-1960s]; From a set of mounted, numbered variously, b/w prints that also include MoMA exhibitions and classes (Box 22, Folder IV.A.vii.2)
    - Children participating, installation views (3 of 6), [1940s-1960s]; From a set of mounted, numbered variously, b/w prints that also include MoMA exhibitions and classes (Box 22, Folder IV.A.vii.3)
    - Children participating, installation views (4 of 6), [1940s-1960s]; From a set of mounted, numbered variously, b/w prints that also include MoMA exhibitions and classes (Box 22, Folder IV.A.vii.4)
    - Children participating, installation views (5 of 6), [1940s-1960s]; From a set of mounted, numbered variously, b/w prints that also include MoMA exhibitions and classes (Box 22, Folder IV.A.vii.5)
    - Children participating, installation views (6 of 6), [1940s-1960s]; From a set of mounted, numbered variously, b/w prints that also include MoMA exhibitions and classes (Box 22, Folder IV.A.vii.6)
    - Equipment used in children's art galleries, 1949-1957; Photographs include views from Children's Art Carnival Milan, Children's Holiday Carnival MoMA: b/w prints (Box 23, Folder IV.A.vii.7)
    - Various locations, 1950s; B/w and color prints and transparencies (Box 23, Folder IV.A.vii.8)
    - MoMA, Brussels, Milan, India, 1950s-1960s; Slide presentation: color and b/w slides (Box 23, Folder IV.A.vii.9)
    - MoMA, Brussels, Barcelona, India, 1950s-1960s; B/w prints (Box 23, Folder IV.A.vii.10)
    - Milan, India, Harlem (1 of 2), [1950s-1960s]; Mounted b/w prints (Box 23, Folder IV.A.vii.11)
    - Milan, India, Harlem (2 of 2), [1950s-1960s]; Mounted b/w prints (Box 23, Folder IV.A.vii.12)
    - MoMA, India, Barcelona, 1955-1957, 1963, 1964; Photographs of children and parents making art; includes contact sheet of MoMA Carnival with D'Amico and print of Carnival construction in India: mounted and unmounted b/w prints (Box 23, Folder IV.A.vii.13)
    - MoMA, Brussels, Milan, Harlem, Barcelona, 1956-1959; Photographs from an original envelope marked "Photos Carnivals & Caravan - model and article": b/w prints (Box 23, Folder IV.A.vii.14)
    - Brussels, Barcelona, [1957-1958]; Photographs of children working, finished works; from an unlabeled box: color slides (Box 23, Folder IV.A.vii.15)
    - Milan, Barcelona, India, 1957-1963; From an original slide carousel marked "incomplete": color slides (Box 23, Folder IV.A.vii.16)
    - India, unidentified, 1957-1963; Photographs of finished works: color slides (Box 23, Folder IV.A.vii.17)
    - Milan, Barcelona, India, 1957-1963; Photographs of children at work, finished works: color slides (Box 23, Folder IV.A.vii.18)
    - India, Harlem, 1960s; Photographs of children, teachers, finished works: color slides (Box 23, Folder IV.A.vii.19)
    - Floor plan, Carnival building and outside areas, [1960]; Unidentified Carnival location: pencil sketch on paper (Box 70, Folder IV.A.vii.20*)
    - India, Harlem, 1963, 1968; Photographs of children, teachers, finished works, models of Children’s Caravan: color slides (Box 23, Folder IV.A.vii.21)
  - Subseries IV.B. "Through the Enchanted Gate,", 1952-[1953]
    - Notes, program information, handwritten and carbon copies of introductory text, 1952, undated (Box 23, Folder IV.B.1)
    - Children working, 1952; Images marked as having been used in "Through the Enchanted Gate": b/w prints (Box 23, Folder IV.B.2)
    - Children's Guide, 1952; Typescript and photocopies (Box 23, Folder IV.B.3)
    - Edited script, [1952]; Original typescript, hand-edited (Box 23, Folder IV.B.4)
    - Edited script, [1952]; Carbon copy (1 of 2) (Box 24, Folder IV.B.5)
    - Edited script, [1952]; Carbon copy (2 of 2) (Box 24, Folder IV.B.6)
    - Children sketching, with television on, [1952-1953]; B/w print, mounted (Box 24, Folder IV.B.7)
    - "Through the Enchanted Gate," "Let's Have a Circus Party," "Make An Imaginary Paper Animal," "Paint How You Feel Inside", June, July 1952; Episodes from the program: four 12" film reels; Note: These films have been transferred to the Museum's Film Study Center which has the proper facilities for storing and screening them. Researchers should contact the Center for further information. Access may be denied due to the films’ physical condition. (Box 24, Folder IV.B.8)
  - Subseries IV.C. Children's Art Caravan, 1960s-1974
    The Art Caravan was designed as a mobile version of the Children's Art Carnival, entirely designed by D'Amico and championed by him after his retirement as Director of the Department of Education. To be contained in a pair of trailers, it would incorporate both a motivations area and an area for children to work creatively under the supervision of trained teachers, similar to the Art Carnival. The project was initially supported by a grant from the John D. Rockefeller, 3rd, Fund in 1968. Subsequently, both the National Endowment for the Humanities and the John D. Rockefeller, 3rd, Fund had promised additional grants, contingent on matching funding. By 1971 MoMA's funding priorities had changed and did not include further support of the Caravan, at which time D'Amico resigned from the project.
    - Plans for educational equipment and furniture, Caravan floor plan, [1960s]; Whiteprints (Box 73, Folder IV.C.1*)
    - Floor plan, [1960s]; Annotated whiteprint; oversize, see flat file 2-2 (Box flat file 2-2, Folder IV.C.2*)
    - Caravan model, 1966, 1967; Color slides (Box 24, Folder IV.C.3)
    - Correspondence, 1967-1971; Re: fundraising, grant applications; includes photocopied TLS D'Amico-Jean D’Autilia (1/19/1971) outlining potential of Caravan; undated extracts from "letters of interest in Art Caravan" by educational organizations (Box 24, Folder IV.C.4)